# Paul-Henry Leemann

Researcher in Pure Mathematics

Université de Neuchâtel Institut de mathématiques 2000 Neuchâtel, Suisse ⊠ Paul-Henry.Leemann@unine.ch '⊞ www.leemann.website



#### Personal Information

Date of Birth April 12, 1987 Citizenship Switzerland

#### Main areas of research

My research interests lie in the intersection of geometric and combinatorial group theory, graph theory and symbolic dynamic. I am particularly interested in groups acting on rooted trees and their (weakly) maximal subgroups, limits and coverings of (Schreier) graphs, rigidity phenomenon in Cayley and Schreier graphs and graphs associated to dynamical systems.

# **Employment**

Since **Université de Neuchâtel**, *Post-Doc*, in Institut de mathématiques, with Alain September 2020 Valette.

2018–2020 **ENS-Lyon**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Post-Doc Labex MILYON

2016–2018  $\,$  **ENS-Lyon**, Post-Doc, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Early Postdoc. Mobility grant supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation

#### Education

2011–2016 **Université de Genève**, *Ph.D. in Mathematics*, "On Subgroups and Schreier Graphs of Finitely Generated Groups", advisor: Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

Mention très bien

2013–2015 Université de Genève, Basic Certificate of Didactic in Mathematics and in Educational Science.

2009–2011 **Université de Genève**, *M. Sc. in Mathematics*, Master-thesis: "Caractères irréductibles des groupes de Coxeter finis", advisors: Pierre de la Harpe and Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

grades: 6/6 (Master-thesis) and 5.7/6 (courses)

2006–2009 Université de Genève, B. Sc. in Mathematics.

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

# Publications and Preprints

- 1. Finitely generated subgroups of branch groups and subdirect products of just infinite groups. (2020). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.16121
- 2. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. (2019). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.06399
- 3. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms, with M. de la Salle. J Algebr Comb (2020). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10801-020-00956-1
- 4. Schreier graphs: Transitivity and Coverings. Internat. J. Algebra Comput., Vol. 26, Issue 1 (2016). www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S021819671650003X
- 5. Weakly maximal subgroups in regular branch groups, with K. Bou-Rabee and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Algebra, Vol. 455 (2016). www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0021869316001046
- Lamplighter groups, de Bruijn graphs, spider-web graphs and their spectra, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, Vol. 49, Number 20 (2016). https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1751-8113/49/20/205004

#### Prizes, Grants and Scientific Visits

- 2016 Vacheron Constantin prize for the best thesis in mathematics, Université de Genève
- 07-12 2015 Semester "Analytic and Geometric Aspects of Probability on Graphs", EPFL, Switzer-land
- 01-04 2014 IHP Semester "Marches aléatoires et géométrie asymptotique des groupes", CIRM and IHP, France
- April 2011 Topology and Geometric Group Theory, Columbus, Ohio, USA

# Conference organisation

March 2013 Co-organizer of the Kervaire seminar "Géométrie des groupes 2013", 10-15 march, Les Diablerets, Switzerland

## Talks (selected)

#### Conferences:

- June 2018 Trees Dynamics and Locally Compact Groups, Heinrich Heine University, Dusseldörf, Germany
- November 2014 Paroles aux jeunes chercheurs en géométrie et dynamique, GDR Platon, *Université* de Bordeaux, France
  - June 2014 "Workshop in Algebra and Geometry", University of Bern, Switzerland Seminars:
  - March 2020 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, *Université de Genève, Switzerland.* Slides: www.leemann.website/slides/weaklymaximal.pdf
    - July 2019 Séminaire Darboux, Montpellier, France
  - January 2017 Rencontre AGIRA, Sète, France
    - May 2015 Ergodic and Geometric Group Theory Seminar, EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

# Teaching Experiences

Since 2016 In ENS Lyon:

- Teaching assistant of "Coverings and fundamental groups" (master)
- Teacher of "Introduction to LATEX" (3rd year class)

2011–2016 Teaching assistant at the University of Genève:

- Advanced course on Combinatorics (master)
- Algebra II: groups, rings, fields, Galois theory (2nd year class)
- Algebra I: linear algebra (1st year class)
- Analysis I: basics of logic and set theory, real analysis (1st year class)
- General mathematics: 1st year class for students of other departments
- Tutoring for first year students
- 2006–2011 Private tutor in mathematics for high school students

# ---- Refereeing

I have been a referee for the following journals: Journal of Algebra, International journal of Algebra and Computation, L'enseignement mathématiques, Journal of Algebra and its Applications.

# Scientific popularization

- 2017 MATHαLYON: interactive workshop in Junior High School, Lyon, France
- 2014-2016 Mentor in the "boussole" curriculum (one week of immersion in the mathematics' department, for High School's students), Genève, Switzerland
- 2012-2016 Facilitator at the University "Open Day", Genève, Switzerland
- 2011-2016 Mathematics' facilitator in Junior High School and High School classes, Genève, Switzerland
  - 2015 Facilitator at the "Science's night", Genève, Switzerland

## Languages

French native

English fluent

German basics

#### Others

Computer skills (IA)TEX (advanced), HTML/CSS and GAP (basics)

Summer camps I have been organizing and running summer camps for children. I have taken part in over thirty camps.

Civilian service 6 months in the physiotherapy's unit of HUG

Sports Telemark skiing (including ski touring), rock climbing, hiking